how does bellow B of brambles interact
with the Theos Gods specifically how
does bellow interact with them and their
if your Devotion to a color is less than
x this God isn't a creature ability this
was initially going to be a short but I
figured there would be too many
questions that I couldn't cover in 60
seconds so in this video I'm going to
cover the four basic scenarios that
could come up with Bellow and the gods
they'll be chaptered below so you can
refer to them in future if you need to
so let's quickly cover the two cards
we'll be looking at first there's Bellow
bard of the brambles a three Mana 33
that says during your turn each
non-equipment artifact and non Ora
enchantment you control with Mana 4 or
greater is a 44 Elemental creature in
addition to its other types and has
indestructible haste and whenever this
creature deals combat damage to a player
draw a card the next card or cards we
need to look at are the Theos Gods
specifically the ones that cost four
minor or more of which there are 17 but
if we looking at just the ones we can
play in a Bellow commander deck there
are currently only five the two versions
of nyia the two versions are poros and
zenos each of the gods are enchantment
creatures however if your Devotion to a
certain color or colors is below the
threshold these gods are not creatures
it's important to understand that both
Bellow's ability and the God's Not a
creature ability are both continuous
effects and when you hear the words
continuous effect AKA anything that
would change the printed information on
a card you know we need to look at
layers let's break this down while I'm
not going to cover layers completely in
this video all you need to know is that
there are seven types of continuous
effects and they apply in order from top
to bottom of the layers list if you
would like to learn more about layers
check out this video
here so looking at Bellow's ability we
can see that they're setting the power
and toughness that's layer 7B they're
changing or adding a type that's layer
four and their adding abilities that's
layer six next if we look at the God's
devotion ability we can see that they're
removing creature type so that takes
place in layer four four the next thing
we need to take note of is that both
Bellow and the gods have their creature
type ad or removing ability trying to
apply on layer four so how do we work
out which one we apply first in this
case we apply them in timestamp order
whichever card enters play first will
have the earlier time stamp and their
ability will be applied first now we
have that out of the way let's jump into
some examples scenario one you played
Bellow first then you played a God and
you do meet the devotion requirements so
we go down the layers list we'll start
at layer four Bellow's ability will
apply first giving the god the elemental
and creature types since we do have
devotion the not a creature ability
doesn't apply here we then get to layer
six and Bellow will give the god
indestructible haste and the draw
and then we finally get to layer 7B and
set the God's power and toughness to
44 scenario two you played Bellow first
then you played a God and you do not
meet the devotion
requirement again we go down the layers
list starting at layer four Bellow's
ability will be applied granting the
elemental and creature types but because
we don't have devotion in this example
the God will then apply there not a
creature ability and remove their
creature type again we apply abilities
that happen on the same layer in
timestamp order Bellow was in play first
so their abilities will be applied first
then the gods we continue through layer
6 and 7B and the God will be a 44
legendary enchantment with
indestructible haste and the drawability
however because it's not a creature it
will not be able to attack scenario 3
and four you played the God first then
you played Bellow and if you've been
keeping up you'll know for these
scenarios it actually doesn't matter if
you have devotion or not let's go
through the
layers once again we'll start at layer
four and let's assume you don't have
devotion so we'll apply the not a
creature ability first then because
Bellow has the later time stamp now
we'll apply their ability second
and give the god back the creature type
along with elemental we'll rinse and
repeat layers 6 and 7B and you'll end up
with a 44 legendary enchantment creature
God Elemental with indestructible haste
and the draw ability the exact same
outcome happens if you do have enough
devotion for your God as well one final
note for all of these examples do
remember that Bellow's ability only
applies during your turn the gods act
like normal on everybody else's turn so
if you want to learn more about layers
be sure to check out this video here
remember to like the video If you
learned something and subscribe because
if you don't I'll make Bellow
accidentally summon the elrazi to
bloombar thanks to the hedron in his
staff thanks for watching and I'll see
you in the next one